Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series X: Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link, 2004; 593040
  Subtitled "A History of 25 Years of Travel Restrictions," the 33-minute film Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link tells the story of efforts to maintain links between the Cuban and American people. Also documented are the activities of many of the anti-Castro groups in Florida and in New Jersey who violently opposed travel between the United States and Cuba. Appearing in the film are US politicians including Republican Senator and former Representative from Arizona Jeff Flake; Republican former Senator and Representative from Idaho, Larry Craig; Democratic former Representative from Massachusetts, Bill Delahunt; and Democratic Massachusetts Representative, Jim McGovern. In the documentary they contend that travel between the countries builds openness and understanding; strengthens family ties; fosters cultural exchange, tourism and trade; and is a constitutional right for all Americans. No raw footage associated with the film is available. Only a completed version of the documentary is included in this series.
  - Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link, 2004; 593041 (Box 73, Dvd 3)
    This is a full-length version of the film Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link.
- Series XI: Holy Father and Gloria, 1985-1991; 479173
  Estela Bravo's 1987 film Holy Father and Gloria El Santo Padre y la Gloria won many awards including Best Documentary on Current Affairs at the San Francisco International Film Festival; Gold Plaque Award at the Chicago International Film Festival; and Best Documentary at the American Film Institute Global Village Festival in New York.
  Carmen Gloria Quintana Arancibia (1968- ) is a Chilean woman who became a symbol of hope for democracy in Chile to many Chileans after she received an embrace and encouragement from Pope John Paul II in 1987. On July 2,1986, Quintana, along with a young photographer, Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri, were participating in a student protest in Santiago. They were attacked and beaten by a patrol of military police, soaked with gasoline, and set on fire. De Negri died of his burns. Gloria suffered second and third degree burns over 62% of her body; she was critically ill and was moved to a hospital in Canada. Although she survived, Gloria was badly disfigured from her burns. When the Pope visited Chile in 1987, she returned and was able to meet with the pontiff in Santiago.
  The 43-minute documentary Holy Father and Gloria (El Santo Padre y la Gloria) was released in 1987 and captures the turbulence of Chile under the Pinochet dictatorship. It traces the story of Carmen Gloria Quintana and her 1987 journey back to Chile to see the Pope. In addition to footage of the Pope's visit and the ongoing protests the documentary includes interviews with Quintana and many others. Among the voices captured are those of elites, particularly young people, who supported the Pinochet government and felt the protests were unnecessary. Footage in this series includes shots of Quintana touring Chile, speeches by the Pope, interviews with Quintana and other Chileans, and historical footage contextualizing Chilean politics.
  - El Santo Padre y la Gloria, 1987; 590455 (Box 73, Dvd 10)
    This is a full-length version of the film Holy Father and Gloria. This film is in Spanish and contains subtitles in English.
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; 2012.044; 593062 (Reel ref2158_01, Reel ref2158_02)
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; 2013.014; 593070; 1 Reels (Reel ref2165)
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; 479184 (Box 44, Cassette ref961, Box 97, Dvd ref961)
    This video contains a complete version of the documentary Holy Father and Gloria. Video quality is poor at the beginning of the video.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:44:08.
  - Holy Father and Gloria, Spanish, 1991 January 14; 479182 (Box 44, Cassette ref960)
  - Holy Father and Gloria "Version 1 First Edit", 1987; 479615 (Box 55, Cassette ref1273)
  - "El Santo Padre y La Gloria 42 minutes (Español)", 1987; 479712 (Box 61, Cassette ref1365)
  - Quintana, Carmen Gloria: Arrival in Chile, 1987; 479708 (Box 60, Cassette ref1361, Box 98, Dvd ref1361)
    This video predominantly features footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana arriving in Chile among crowds of supporters. It contains brief segments in which Quintana speaks with reporters and describes the medical treatment she received in Canada, and expresses her support of the Chilean youth movement. It contains footage of Quintana at rallies and a Catholic mass. The last 15 minutes feature Quintana and her supporters outside of a jail attempting to gain entry and meet with political prisoners.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:50:25.
  - Quintana, Carmen Gloria: Interview (Debryando Street), 1987 May 4; cuid388; 467244 (Box 39, Cassette ref809, Box 95, Dvd ref809)
    This video features youth in Chile celebrating the return of Carmen Gloria Quintana, and a brief interview with Quintana. The first several minutes feature children drawing doves and other tributes to Quintana on the street. At minute 2:58 the video changes to an interview with Quintana. She discusses her hope of meeting with the Pope, and her surprise at the warm welcome she received upon her return. She says that she hopes to continue fighting and speaking out against the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet, but acknowledges that protest is still very difficult. She also discusses a button featuring the Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri, who died when they were both attacked by members of the Chilean military and burned. She explains that she hopes to be a representative of Rojas's memory. At minute 10:56 the footage changes to Chilean youths discussing a mural of Quintana and Rojas, painted at the location where they were attacked. A young woman and young man speak with Bravo about the significance of Quintana and Rojas to the youth movement in Chile.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:27.
  - Footage: "Carmen, Rodrigo, Pope;" "Completo", 1987; 479709 (Box 60, Cassette ref1362)
  - Footage: "Funeral Rodrigo, Cemetery, Carmen Gloria", 1987; 479711 (Box 67, Cassette ref1364)
    According to Estela Bravo, this video contains 13 minutes of footage of the funeral of Rodrigo Rojas, followed by brief footage of young people being arrested. It also contains pictures of Carmen Gloria before she was burned. Finally, there is footage of a young woman - Valesa - who left Chile with her family but was allowed to return later. This footage is from the film Returning to Chile.
  - Footage: Parque O'Higgins and Carmen Gloria, 1987; 479713 (Box 67, Cassette ref1366)
    According to Bravo, this video contains footage of the Pope speaking at Parque O'Higgins followed by Carmen Gloria in her home in Chile, with family and friends.
    Parque O'Higgins is a public park in the center of Santiago, Chile. Pope John Paul II (in his 1987 visit) led a beautification ceremony for Saint Teresa of the Andes. Because of the violence that broke out between the Chilean police force and crowds protesting Pinochet's dictatorship, the ceremony was suspended until the situation calmed.
  - Footage: O'Higgins Park, Santiago: Protests at Pope's Mass, 1987; 467216 (Box 43, Cassette ref837, Box 97, Dvd ref837)
    This video begins with footage of violent clashes between the police and protestors at O'Higgins Park in Santiago, Chile where Pope John Paul II delivered Mass to a large crowd in 1987. The footage shows protestors building makeshift barriers and throwing objects while police try to disperse them. The footage focuses primarily on the crowd, and does not show the Pope speaking, although he can be heard through a loudspeaker. The video features several on-the-street interviews: one with a man opposed to the protests, one with a local journalist, and one with a young protester. The end of this video also features an interview with exiled Chilean Socialist leader Clodomiro Almeyda. In the interview Almeyda discusses why he chose to return to Chile during the Pope's visit to the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:33.
  - Footage: "Chile, Students, Gloria", 1987; cuid790; 479714 (Box 60, Cassette ref1367, Box 98, Dvd ref1367)
    This video features interviews with three different groups of students in Chile. Estela Bravo asks the students, who are from middle and upper-class schools, about their opinions of Chilean President Augusto Pinochet, Pope John Paul II's visit, and the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana. Students from the various groups express different opinions on these topics, and many of the students who come from upper-class households express their support of Pinochet. They argue that the people protesting his government are mistaken and supporters of terrorism. Several students express their admiration for Pinochet, and contend that he saved the country from communism. Other students express their dislike of Pinochet, and contend that the students who support him are uninformed and are not in a position to understand the political situation of the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:28.
  - Footage: Chilean Boy and the Police, 1987 March 4; 479720 (Box 60, Cassette ref1373, Box 98, Dvd ref1373)
    This video begins with footage of a mother trying to talk to Chilean police about her son. She explains that she heard that her son, who was 9 years old at the time the footage was recorded, was injured by police after they chased him into a house. The woman attempts to find out what happened to her son and where he was taken, but the police do not give her any information. The video then focuses on the house where the boy was attacked. The family in the house explains that they police chased the boy, broke down their door, and hit the young boy in the head causing him to bleed significantly. Several of the children and adults in the house describe witnessing the event. They also talk about police treatment of the poor and substandard living conditions in their community.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:18.
  - Footage: "Pinochet greets Pope at the airport", 1987; 479552 (Box 52, Cassette ref1210)
  - Footage: Rojas Grave and Interview with son of Orlando Letelier, 1987; cuid389; 467243 (Box 39, Cassette ref810, Box 95, Dvd ref810)
    Juan Pablo Letelier was the son of Orlando Letelier. Orlando Letelier was a Chilean diplomat under the government of Salvador Allende. He left Chile as a refugee of the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet, and was assassinated by Pinochet's secret police in Washington D.C. in 1976.
    This video mostly features an interview with Juan Pablo Letelier. The first few seconds of the video contain footage of the grave of Chilean dissident Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri. It quickly changes to an interview with Letelier, which begins with a discussion about his early life and his father's assassination. He discusses leaving Chile when he was 3 years old, and returning to Chile later in life. He also talks about his involvement in leftist political movements in Chile and his participations in Chile's Socialist Youth. He discusses the significance of the visit of Pope John Paul II in 1987, and the 1989 general elections. Letelier talks at length about the political climate in Chile at the end of the 1980s discussing the country's transition to democracy and the influence of youth activism. The video quality is poor in many places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:58.
  - Footage: College Stadium (the Pope speaking and Carmen Gloria in the audience) and Cemetery, 1987; 479715 (Box 67, Cassette ref1368)
  - Footage: Police Brutality, 1985 September 4; 479716 (Box 67, Cassette ref1369)
  - Footage: Carmen Gloria Quintana Complete Visit Jail, circa 1987; 479717 (Box 60, Cassette ref1370, Box 98, Dvd ref1370)
    This video features footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana attempting to gain entry into a jail in Chile to meet with political prisoners. A spokesman for Quintana explains she is there to express her solidarity with prisoners. The bulk of the footage features a crowd waiting outside the jail hoping to gain entry. This video duplicates content contained on video ref1361.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:03.
  - Footage: "Carmen Gloria in victory", 1987; 467242 (Box 39, Cassette ref811, Box 97, Dvd ref811)
    This video begins with brief footage of two Chilean youths at a mural memorializing the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana and Rodrigo Rojas who were burned by Chilean military police in 1986. The video then changes to footage of Quintana arriving at a rally in her honor. Much of this footage features shots of the crowd gathered in anticipation of Quintana's arrival. At minute 13:00 Quintana addresses the crowd and describes her encounter with the military, in which she and Rojas were doused with gasoline and then lit on fire. At the time of her speech, she explains that it has been 10 months since the event and notes that she has been left badly disfigured and Rojas has died.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:09.
  - Footage: March Final Against Torture, 1987 February 4; 479718 (Box 60, Carton ref1371, Box 98, Dvd ref1371)
    The beginning of this video features an interview with a man and a woman in a church in Chile. They discuss their involvement in the resistance movement against the Pinochet government and the violence they have witnessed in the country. The interview focuses on the government's use of torture against citizens. The woman shares specific examples of torture used against Chilean citizens, discuss police interrogation methods, and describes the psychological effects of state-sponsored violence. At minute 12:00 the video features a demonstration against the government, and protestors can be seen clashing briefly with the police. Bravo interviews members of the crowd about why they are at the protest, and about their expectations for the upcoming 1987 visit of Pope John Paul II.
  - National Stadium / Pope Compilation, 1987; 467503 (Box 23, Cassette ref550)
  - "Pope, Chile, Street, Carmen Gloria, Funeral Rodrigo," and Others, 1987; 479710 (Box 60, Cassette ref1363)
  - Carmen Gloria " Ernesto's Copy", 1987; 467212 (Box 43, Cassette ref878)
  - "2 Carmen Gloria Completa", 1987; 467800 (Box 11, Cassette ref253)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; 467423 (Box 32, Cassette ref630)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; 467369 (Box 31, Cassette ref684)
  - "TV Espanola Programa Editado - Pinochet - the Pope - Chile - Carmen Gloria", 1987; 467334 (Box 38, Cassette ref719)
  - "Hotel Capri - press conference - Estela Bravo - Juan Vilar", circa 1987; 467333 (Box 38, Cassette ref720)
  - "Torture photos - Pinochet speech", circa 1987; 467327 (Box 38, Cassette ref726)
  - "Pepe Carrasco CNN Pinochet", circa 1986; 467251 (Box 39, Cassette ref802, Box 97, Dvd ref802)
    Jose Humberto "Pepe" Carrasco Tapia (1943-1986) was a Chilean journalist opposed to the military dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. He was assassinated on September 7, 1986.
    This video features an assortment of footage filmed in Chile around 1986. It begins with footage of protesters clashing with military police. It then changes to shots of newspaper headlines announcing the arrival of socialist politician Clodomiro Almeyda. At minute 9:29 the footage changes to edits of a CNN Atlanta news report on the political climate in Chile. The footage features several segments which focus on a failed national strike, the death of journalist José Carrasco, and the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. After the CNN report ends the video features additional raw footage of protests, funerals, government events, and a short speech by Pinochet denouncing communists in the country. The end of the video features footage of an impoverished community.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:01:59.
  - "Carmen Gloria - Final Victory - Cemetery", 1987 May 4; 467250 (Box 39, Cassette ref803)
  - "Chile Carmen Gloria", 1987; 467217 (Box 43, Cassette ref836)
  - "Film festival - Homage to Estela Bravo for Holy Father and Gloria"(about Bravo), 1987; 467328 (Box 38, Cassette ref725)
  - "Photos - Carmen Gloria - the Pope speaks - Dibuyos (drawings)", 1987; 467330 (Box 38, Cassette ref723)
  - Carmen Gloria Quintana Arriving in Chile / Allemand, Maria Olga: Interview, 1987; 467332 (Box 38, Cassette ref721, Box 97, Dvd ref721)
    This video begins with footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana arriving in Chile in 1987. She is greeted by crowds and speaks to reporters. At minute 5:00 the video changes to an interview with Chilean photographer Maria Olga Allemand. In the interview Allemand talks about being shot while photographing a demonstration. She describes the event, and the people who helped her immediately after she was shot. She discusses the support she received from her community and her desire to continue working as a photographer despite the risk of being injured again. The end of the video changes back to footage of Quintana, and features portion of a speech she delivered to a village in Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:06.
  - "Carmen Gloria Bump", 1987; 467220 (Box 43, Cassette ref833, Box 97, Dvd ref833)
    This video contains various segments featuring Carmen Gloria Quintana in Chile. Segments include footage of Quintana speaking at rallies, traveling through crowds, attending mass, attempting to speak to political prisoners, and visiting the grave of her friend Rodrigo Rojas. The video also shows short clips of demonstrations on the streets of Chile and a speech by Pope John Paul II. Segments that appear on this tape are duplicated on other videos contained in this series.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:13.
- Series XII: The Hour of the People, 1985-1988; 479648
  This 39-minute film Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo ) documents the Uruguay's return to democracy, following a peaceful transition from a military dictatorship that ruled the country between 1973 and 1985. This series includes copies of the full-length documentary, as well as interview footage with Uruguayan Communist Party leader Jaime Perez.
  - La Hora del Pueblo (Master), 1985; cuid782; 479649 (Box 57, Cassette ref1306, Box 96, Dvd ref1306)
    This video contains a full version of the short documentary Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:56.
  - La Hora del Pueblo, 1985; cuid788; 479650 (Box 57, Cassette ref1307, Box 96, Dvd ref1307)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:37.
  - The Hour of the People, 1985; cuid783; 479685 (Box 59, Cassette ref1342, Box 96, Dvd ref1342)
    This video contains a complete version of the short film Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo). Video quality of this recording is intermittently poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:54:45.
  - Perez, Jaime: Interview, circa 1985; cuid784; 479651 (Box 57, Cassette ref1308, Box 96, Dvd ref1308)
    Jaime Perez was a Jewish union leader in Uruguay. He was imprisoned for 10 years by the government of Uruguay because of his leadership in the Communist Party of the Uruguay.
    In this interview Uruguayan politician Jaime Perez begins by discussing his travels to Cuba in the early 1970s and meeting Fidel Castro. He then talks about his 10-year imprisonment in Uruguay by the country's military dictatorship. He describes Uruguay's transition to democracy and the influence of the country's foreign debt on that process. He explains that he is optimistic about the transition to democracy, but contends that the process has just begun and that the country has a long history of repression and disappearance of political dissidents that needs to be addressed. At the end of the interview he expresses his gratitude to Castro and Cuba for supporting the Communist Party in Uruguay and its fight against the military dictatorship.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:28:06.
- Series XIII: Mandela and Fidel, 2013; 590489
  This series contains a copy of the Bravo documentary Mandel and Fidel, which documents the friendship between Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro. No clips or raw footage associated with this film is included in the series. Instead, much of the footage used in this 30-minute documentary was drawn from earlier films including Namibia: The Last Colony (1990), Mandela in Cuba (1991), and Fidel The Untold Story (2000).
  The film begins with Nelson Mandela's attendance at the Namibian independence celebrations in March of 1990, a month following his release from prison. He meets with Cuban officials and expresses his gratitude for Cuba's assistance in the war in Angola and for its role in the Namibian war of independence. The next year Mandela visits Cuba. The documentary follows the relationship for several more years including Castro's attendance at Mandela's inauguration in 1994 and Fidel's visit to Robben Island to see where Mandela was imprisoned.
  - Mandela and Fidel, 2013; 590490 (Box 73, Dvd 4)
    This is a full-length version of the film Mandela and Fidel.
- Series XIV: Mandela in Cuba, 1991; 479077
  In 1991 Nelson Mandela visited Cuba during a tour to Latin American. Then President of the African National Congress, Mandela used the tour to lobby countries like Brazil, Mexico, and Venezuela to maintain sanctions against South Africa's white minority government, and support a national unity government in Pretoria. Mandela made a three-day stop in Cuba during the tour to meet with Fidel Castro. Mandela and Castro had never met before the visit, but the two shared admiration for one another stemming from Cuba's support of Angolan and Namibian independence.
  Mandela in Cuba documents Nelson Mandela's three-day visit to Cuba in July of 1991. He attended the celebrations marking the 38th anniversary of the 1953 attack on the Moncada garrison. The series contains a full-length copy of the documentary and footage shot during Mandela's visit. The footage shows speeches and events surrounding the visit, as well as clips of Nelson and Winnie Mandela touring historical sites in Cuba.
  - Mandela in Cuba, 1991; 479078 (Box 71, Cassette ref947, Box 85, Dvd ref947)
    This is a full-length version of the film Mandela in Cuba. This film is in English.
  - Mandela in Cuba, 1991; 467380 (Box 93, Cassette ref673, Box 83, Dvd ref673)
  - Mandela, Nelson: Press Conference in Cuba, 1991; 467912 (Box 5, Cassette ref141, Box 77, Dvd ref141)
    This footage includes about ten minutes of questions and answers at a press conference. Mandela's responses to questions can be heard clearly, but many of the reporters' questions and translations are difficult to hear. In this recording Estela Bravo asks Mandela a question, which can be heard clearly. Additionally, there are places where imaging is poor and scenes are difficult to view.
  - "Mandela Press Conference in Havana", 1991; 467896 (Box 7, Cassette ref157)
  - Fidel and Mandela in Matanzas: Footage at beginning of rally, 1991 July 26; 467350 (Box 87, Cassette ref703, Box 83, Dvd ref703)
    This footage documents the early parts of a July 1991 rally at Matanzas with Nelson Mandela, honoring the 38th anniversary of the Moncada assault that led to Fidel Castro's seizure of power. The footage begins with the singing of the Cuban anthem and an introduction to the event. During the event there are introductions of notable attendees including Daniel Ortega of Nicaragua. Castro speaks to each of the individuals. The footage also shows other Cuban dignitaries who attended the event including Raul Castro and Juan Almeida. This recording is in Spanish.
  - Fidel and Mandela in Matanzas: Speech, Fidel Castro, 1991 July 26; 467299 (Box 94, Cassette ref754, Box 83, Dvd ref754)